Okay, so in this video, I want to discuss
three types of life cycles.
The first life cycle I want to talk about
is this one called the Project Lifecycle.
And the Project Life Cycle
refers to the beginning of
the project all the way
until the end of the project.
That is referred to as a project life
cycle.
The importance of that is that in-between,
there are many different phases,
many different iterations, many different
sprints.
And it all depends on the type of project,
where it's an agile project, predictive
project, and what industry we're talking
about and so on and so forth.
Every industry manages projects
differently, remember.
So an IT project is managed very
differently to a construction project.
And if we're talking, say, predictive,
there's going to be different phases.
IT projects are going to have different
phases to a construction project, right?
So there's many, many different phases
within a project life cycle.
PMI have no standards whatsoever on
phases.
They're basically saying you break your
project down into whatever
phase makes sense.
So again, a construction project,
marketing project, think of all these
different, pharmaceutical project,
every project is going to have different
phases, every industry, every organization,
in fact, might have their own phases.
PMI have no standards for phases.
Depending on the industry, you break a
phase down into, you know, whatever,
or you break a project down into whatever
phase makes sense.
However, each phase, right, remember we
talked about the initiating, planning,
execute, monitoring, controlling,
and closing, right?
Those are the process groups.
Each phase is going to involve each of
those five process groups.
Those five process groups are referred to
as the project management lifecycle.
So each phase, then, we're going to
include those five process groups.
However, I first want to talk about some
characteristics of the project life cycle.
So again, remember, the project life cycle
then refers to the
full life of the project.
So this is the start of the project.
So on the x-axis here, we have the
timeline.
So this is the start of the project.
This is the end of the project.
And then these basic characteristics I'm
going to be talking about, like we're
going to distinguish them between low and
high.
Now, in between, there's going to be many,
many different phases.
Phases are not shown here because every
project is going to have different phases.
We're just looking at very, very overall
high level.
And again, here, we're mostly looking at
predictive, right?
Think of predictive.
Now, the first characteristic I want to
refer to is stakeholder influence.
So your stakeholders'
influence is going to
be highest at the
beginning of the project.
right you're relying on your key
stakeholders if they're giving you the
direction of the project they're giving
you requirements if they want to add in
additional requirements at the beginning
it's up to them it's their prerogative
it's their project so stakeholders
influence is going to be the highest right
at the beginning of the project now as
time goes by along the project right then
their influence is going to get less and
less and why because well you're the
project manager you're the command and
control project manager.
So you can give pushback, right?
You are one then, you
are the one that is making
a decision about the
direction of the project.
You are the one that's
making decisions about
what work needs to be done on the project.
Right, so the influence is going to be
highest.
Stakeholder's influence is going to be
highest at the beginning.
If, for example, halfway through the
project, your senior stakeholders or,
you know, a key stakeholder wants to add
in additional requirements, you as a
project manager can give pushback at the
project.
point.
You can say I wouldn't
recommend this or this is going
to be the impact on the
project and so and so forth.
So their influence is going to be highest
at the beginning and then gradually get
less and less as you go through the
project.
Same with another characteristic I want to
mention, risk and uncertainty.
Now when it comes to project management,
risk is an uncertainty.
Risk does not mean danger.
Risk always means uncertainty.
And there's an entire section on risk,
on risk management, right?
But generally, there's going to be much
higher uncertainty at the beginning of the
project than there is towards the end of
the project.
Risk is going to be highest at the
beginning.
Uncertainty is going to be highest at the
beginning, especially, you know,
since we're thinking about, since we're
talking about predictive projects here.
At the beginning of a
project, you don't know if
you're going to be over
budget behind schedule, right?
You don't know that at the beginning.
In fact, on a predictive project,
you don't even know who all of your team
members are going to be right at the
beginning.
Team members are coming and going as
required on a project.
So there's going to be a much higher cone
of uncertainty at the beginning of a
project than there is towards the end of
the project.
So that's what they mean
when they say risk and
uncertainty gradually
decreases throughout the project.
Towards the end of the project,
you can determine with some degree of
certainty, how much over budget or under
budget we're going to be, how much ahead
of schedule, behind schedule we're going
to be.
That's not clear at the beginning.
Another characteristic then is a resource
utilization and rate of expenditure.
That's not going to be
very high at the beginning
because you don't have too
many people on your project.
You know, you're just doing some initial
planning.
But then as more activities are performed,
as you start using more resources,
more team members, raw materials,
equipment, it's going to, your cost,
your expenditure rate is going to,
increase.
Resource utilization is going to increase.
And then as it's going to peak at some
point, but then as you're going towards
the end of the project, you don't use as
many resources.
You don't use as many raw materials,
for example.
Some of those machines are not needed
anymore.
Some team members can roll off the
project.
So expenditure rate, a resource
utilization is going to start decreasing.
Now let's talk about cost of changes.
I think everybody would agree,
in a predictive project at least.
Cost of changes is going to exponentially
increase as you go through the project,
right?
You want to add in additional requirements
at the beginning of the project?
Cheap and easy to do.
You want to add those same requirements
towards the end of the project,
much more expensive.
Cost of change is going to be much more
expensive.
On a predictive project, what happens in
an Agile project?
Agile allows for change, remember.
The whole idea of Agile is, that it allows
for change.
And so cost of changes are going to be a
little bit more flatter.
Now, it's not going to be exact.
It's not going to be completely straight,
completely flat.
It's just going to increase slightly,
right?
Just very, very slightly, because the
whole agile environment allows for change.
So this is the project lifecycle and some
characteristics of the project life cycle.
Now let's talk about the project
management lifecycle.
and the project management life cycle then
refers to the five process groups, right?
This, you could use this acronym here.
IPEC, initiating, planning, executing, CFA
controlling, as a monitoring
controlling, CFA closing.
And these are the five project management,
or rather, these are the five process
groups that make up the project management
life cycle.
So whenever you hear the term project
management lifecycle, It refers to these
five process groups, initiating,
planning, executing, monitoring,
controlling, and closing.
And as a project manager, you pick and
choose which one of these processes and
which one of these process groups is going
to be relevant for your project.
So remember, the five process groups have
many processes.
There's 49 processes in PIMBox 6.
You pick and choose which one is relevant.
Now, also, the five process groups are
performed simultaneously.
Right.
You could be planning, execute, monitoring,
controlling, all at the same time.
Right.
Now, which of these
processes you're going to be
performing for which phase
that is known as tailoring.
Now, the other life cycle then is this
one called the product life cycle, right?
And product lifecycle refers to the full
life of the product from its starting,
from its inception to its demise.
Right.
And most of that is ongoing operations.
And so, Most of that, so
really, most of the product
life cycle is beyond the
scope of the PMP exam.
However, on the next slide,
I'm just going to be talking about
just some basic principles
behind the product life cycle.
However, just note, every
project has a different project
life cycle, because project
life cycle refers to phases.
Every project has different phases.
Every product is going to have a different
product life cycle, right?
It's from its inception to its demise.
Every product will have a different
product life cycle, but every product.
project is going to have the same project
management lifecycle, which refers to
these five process groups, initiating,
planning, executing, monitoring,
controlling and closing.
Now, let's talk about the product
lifecycle then.
And as I said, this is from inception to
its demise.
And most of that is going to be ongoing
operations.
Now, every product is going to have a
different product lifecycle.
But these are just the basic, basic
stages.
involved, just the basic stages.
So the first stage really is to create the
product, right?
So which is a project?
You have a project to actually create the
product.
Then the product goes to
an introduction stage, right,
where you introduce this
product out into the market.
Sales are generally going to be slow to
pick up, right?
Just maybe some early adopters there.
People don't really know much about this
product.
The sales are going to be slow to pick up.
Then you have what's known as a growth
stage, where sales, you know, the more
marketing you do, the more advertising,
the more sales are going to increase,
growth stage.
Then you have the maturity.
At this point, your sales are leveled off.
You're not making any more new sales.
And then you have the decline and then
finally, you know, end of life where the,
you know, product is now obsolete.
Now, as I said, every product is going to
have a different product life cycle.
This is just a very, very high level.
or rather these are just a very high-level
stages.
Every product is going to have a different
product life cycle.
But in between the product life cycle,
right, you may have different projects.
You may have projects to, say, improve the
process or upgrade the
product, add new features.
Right.
So, you know, there might be projects
within the product lifecycle.